## Mehrad Ansari

102 Suburban Ct. Apt 4, Rochester NY 14620 +1 (573) 578-8850 Mehrad.Ansari@rochester.edu GitHub YouTube Personal Page

Summary: A detail-oriented chemical engineer with a strong background in computational modeling, data science and programming supported by research and professional work experience in process design and optimization.

### **Education**

#### **Doctor of Philosophy in Chemical Engineering**

University of Rochester, Rochester, NY

(August 2023)

GPA: 3.8

#### Master of Science in Chemical/Environmental Engineering

(May 2018)

Missouri University of Science and Technology (UMR), Rolla, MO

**GPA: 3.8** 

**Publication**: Thesis: "Numerical Modeling of Capillary-driven Flow in Open Microchannels: An Implication of Optimized Wicking Fabric Design""

# **Bachelor of Science in Chemical Engineering**

(July 2015)

University of Tehran, Iran

GPA: 3.4

Publication: Thesis: "Experimental Setup and Optimization for Electro-catalytical Generation of Hydroxyl Radicals in Wastewater Treatment"

# Work Experience and Practical Training

**Research Assistant** (2019 - present)

University of Rochester, Rochester, NY

- Developed a plugin with TensorFlow GPU-accelerated operations combined with HOOMD-Blue molecular dynamics simulation engine (HOOMD-TF)
- Developed a maximum entropy biasing epidemiology model to study COVID-19 trajectory in NY state
- Developed a web-app for gelator transparency classification using Kernel ridge regression with TensorFlow.JS
- Developed an automated module on a Raspberry-Pi for real-time monitoring of HPC using Python, JS and HTML
- Implemented finite difference analysis in python to study 2D shallow water dynamics
- Implemented Monte Carlo simulations in MATALB to study evolution of spin configurations of a ferromagnet using the Ising model

### Lead CFD Analyst at Missouri S&T Solar Car Design Team

(2016 - 2018)

Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO

- Developed validated wind tunnel simulations in STAR-CCM+ for aerodynamic optimization of the solar car
- Improved aerodynamic design efficiency prior to manufacturing

**Research Assistant** (2016 - 2018)

Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO

- Numerical modeling of multiphase flow in open microfluidics using ANSYS and STAR-CCM +
- Data analysis and model verification
- Reduced simulation run-time by developing an algorithm for Adaptive Mesh Refinement (AMR)
- Increased solver's stability by developing an algorithm for Adaptive Time Step

## **Manufacturing Process Modeling Intern**

(May-Dec 2017)

The Goodyear Tire & Rubber Company, Akron, OH

- Phase-change heat transfer modeling and optimization of tire vulcanization process in ANSYS
- Model verification based on plant data and analytical solution
- Utilized assets more efficiently through MATLAB post processing and automating the simulation process using OPTIMUS
- Provided faster simulation results using Adaptive Mesh Refinement and High-Performance Computing
- GUI development and coupling ANSYS with MATLAB for time-effective post processing

### Teaching Assistant of "Applied Numerical Methods in CFD"

(Jan-May 2017)

Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO

- Lectured on Finite Difference Analysis in fluid dynamics, heat and mass transfer using MATLAB
- Organized CFD and programming workshops for ANSYS and Star-CCM +

# Mehrad Ansari

102 Suburban Ct. Apt 4, Rochester NY 14620 +1 (573) 578-8850 Mehrad.Ansari@rochester.edu GitHub YouTube Personal Page

# **Work Experience and Practical Training**

## Teaching Assistant of "Process Control"

University of Tehran, Iran

> Tutored undergraduate students in process control using MATLAB and VisSim

Engineering Intern (July-Sept 2014)

Emden-Leer University of Applied Sciences, Germany

> Experimental optimization in advanced oxidation process (AOP) for wastewater treatment

President of IAESTE Iran (Apr 2013-July 2014)

(International Association for the Exchange of Students for Technical Experience)

Led a team of college students that prepared technical internships internationally

**MATLAB Programming Tutor** 

(July-Sept 2011)

(Jan-Mar 2015)

(2014-2015)

University of Tehran, Iran

Organized advanced programming workshops for engineering students

### **Computer Skills**

MATLAB	STAR-CCM+	ANSYS	SolidWorks
OpenFOAM	COMSOL Multi-Physics	Polymath	Mathematica
ASPEN	AUTOCAD	Mathcad	JavaScript
CATIA	OPTIMUS	Python	HTML

### **Honors and Awards**

Earl W. Costich Graduate Fellowship (May 2020
---

Department of Chemical Engineering, University of Rochester

First place winner: 2017 Mike Alizadeh Scholarship (Aug 2017)

American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE)

Recognized reviewer: Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering (May 2016)

First place winner MATLAB programming contest (Mar 2014)

"University of Sharif Computer-Aided Chemical Engineering Contest (SC<sub>3</sub>)"

Sharif University of Technology, Iran

## **Memberships and Volunteer Work**

American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE) (July 2016-Present)

Representative member of Scientific Committee in "15<sup>th</sup> Iranian National

Congress of Chemical Engineering (ICHEC)"

University of Tehran

Head and representative member of scientific committee in "Underground (Jan-May 2014)

Oil and Gas Storage (UGOS) Conference & Exhibition"

University of Tehran

## **Certificates**

"Optimization Techniques in Chemical Engineering" (Feb 2016)

Missouri University of Science and Technology

"Theory of Piping and Pipeline Designs" (Sept 2012)

Tehran Institute of Technology, Iran